# LION BEHRENS

## March 2019

☆ lionbehrens.netlify.com ♥@LionBehrens ☑ behrens@uni-mannheim.de ५+49 621 181-3441 University of Mannheim, B6 30-32, Room 322, 68131 Mannheim, Germany

### **SUMMARY**

I am an early career academic researching comparative politics and quantitative methods. In my substantive work, I study electoral fraud and legislative behavior. To this end, I apply statistical modeling, Monte Carlo simulation, and machine-learning techniques. Methodically, I explore the merits that Bayesian statistics provides for inference in the political sciences, particularly when facing challenges such as evidence synthesis and multi-method research.

# **CURRENT POSITION**

Research Associate

June 2018 - ongoing

Collaborative Research Center 884, University of Mannheim

Project C7 "Political attention and the substance of legislative reform"

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. Political Science Sep 2018 - ongoing

Graduate School of Economic and Social Sciences, University of Mannheim

M.Sc. Methodology and Statistics Sep 2016 - May 2018

Utrecht University

B.A. Political Science (with distinction) Sep 2013 - July 2016

University of Bremen

## PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Behrens, Lion and Ingo Rohlfing. 2018. "Not so different in present attitudes and behavior, but expected future membership - A technical replication of a study of party youth in six European democracies". Research & Politics, Online Only, 1-5.

#### WORK IN PROGRESS

Behrens, Lion and Rebecca M Kuiper. "A Bayesian method for synthesizing evidence from heterogeneous statistical models". Working Paper.

Behrens, Lion and Ingo Rohlfing. "Bayesian nested analysis". In preparation.

Buskens, Vincent, Werner Raub, Lion Behrens, Rebecca M. Kuiper and Irene Klugkist. "Embeddedness effects on trust in social and economic exchange: A Bayesian analysis of evidence from four studies". *In preparation*.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# Teaching Assistant

Applied Bayesian Statistics, Utrecht Summer School

Structural Equation Modeling with Mplus, Utrecht Summer School

Business Statistics, De Bijlespartner Amsterdam

July 2017 March 2017 - May 2017

May 2018

#### Tutor

Instrumental Variables in Psychology, B.A. Thesis, Utrecht University, by Hugo Hanema

January 2017 - May 2017

#### PRESENTATIONS

"Political Trust and Political Participation - The Micro-Level Relationship and Its Macro-Level Dependencies", Semiannual Meeting of the Ecuadorian Political Science Association (AECIP), Quito April 2016

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Internships

GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences, Mannheim

January - March 2018

Research assistance for Oshrat Hochman analyzing European Social Survey data

FLACSO - Latin American Social Science Institute, Quito

February - April 2016

Research on political participation analyzing data from the Latin American Public Opinion Project

# Research Assistantships

Department for Methods & Statistics, Utrecht University, Prof. Rens van de Schoot, Ph.D.

Bremen International Graduate School of Social Sciences, Prof. Ingo Rohlfing, Ph.D.

Research Center on Inequality and Social Policy, Bremen, Prof. Michael Windzio

Collaborative Research Center 597, Bremen University, Natascha Zaun, Ph.D.

Jan 17 - March 18

April - July 2016

March - August 2015

July - December 2014

# ADDITIONAL TRAINING

Multilevel analysis using HLM, GESIS Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences	2015
Hot Topics in Machine Learning, GESS, University of Mannheim	2018
Computational Text Analysis, GESS, University of Mannheim	2018
Theory Building and Causal Inference, GESS, University of Mannheim	2018

### GRANTS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Full scholarship grant, Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes	2016 - 2018
Full scholarship grant, Konrad-Adenauer-Stiftung	2013 - 2016

## INVITED REFEREE

Research & Politics

#### **SKILLS**

## Computing

R, Stata, Mplus, SPSS, HLM, JAGS, Shiny, LATEX, Markdown

## Methodical

General Linear Model, Multilevel Analysis, Structural Equation Modeling, Instrumental Variables, Propensity Score Matching, Statistical Computing and Simulation, Bayesian Methods

#### Languages

German: Native, English: Fluent, Spanish: Oral Fluency

# REFERENCES

Prof. Ingo Rohlfing, PhD

Center for Comparative Politics

University of Cologne

Phone:  $+49\ 221\ 470-89104$ Email: i.rohlfing@uni-koeln.de

Prof. Thomas Gschwend, PhD

Quantitative Methods in the Social Sciences

University of Mannheim Phone: +49 621 181 2087

Email: gschwend@uni-mannheim.de